<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="TroubleShooting"><info><title xml:id="ProActiveTroubleshooting_38">ProActive Troubleshooting</title></info>
	
	<indexterm>
		<primary>Troubleshooting</primary>
	</indexterm>

   <para>In this section, we present common problems encountered while trying to
   use ProActive. For further assistance, or if you cannot solve a problem, feel free to post your question on the
   ProActive mailing list <email>proactive@ow2.org</email>. Make sure that you include a
   precise description of your problem along with a full copy of your error
   message.</para>

   <section xml:id="Commonproblems_38"><info><title>Common problems</title></info>

      <para>If you encounter any problem with installing ProActive and running
      examples, please make sure you have correctly followed all the steps
      described in the previous chapter. If it doesn't help, here is a list of the most common
      mistakes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Permission denied when trying to launch
            scripts under Linux</emphasis> - Files have the wrong permissions set.
            You have to change permissions by executing <literal>chmod -R 744 *.sh</literal>
            in the <literal>ProActive/examples</literal> directory. The command will
            set the files to executable and readable for all users and also writeable for the current user.
            </para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Java complains about not being able to
            find the ProActive classes</emphasis> - Your <literal>CLASSPATH</literal>
            environment variable does not contain the entry for classes belonging to ProActive,
            ASM, Log4, Xerces, Fractal, Ibis or BouncyCastle. Normally, only
            <literal>ProActive.jar</literal> must be in
            your <literal>CLASSPATH</literal> since the other libraries are indexed into the ProActive.jar file.
            However, if these others libraries are not in the same directory than ProActive.jar, then you have to
            insert them into your <literal>CLASSPATH</literal>.
            In any case, you can try to include them to your <literal>CLASSPATH</literal> but it might lead to some
            problems under Windows since the command line to launch applications will be very long and Windows will
            probably reject it.
            </para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Java complains about denial of
            access</emphasis> - If you get the following exceptions, you probably
            didn't change the file java.policy as described in <xref linkend="Create_Java_Policy"/>.</para>

            <programlisting><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/trouble_shooting/java_policy_error.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Java complains on log4j
            initialization</emphasis> - If you get the following message, you
            probably made a mistake when giving the
            <literal>-Dlog4j.configuration</literal> property to the java command.
            Be sure that the given path is right, try also to add <literal>file:</literal> before the
            path.</para>
            <programlisting><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/trouble_shooting/log4j_notfound_error.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Examples and compilation do not work at
            all under Windows system</emphasis> - Check whether your java installation
            is not in a path containing spaces like <literal>C:\Program Files\java or
            C:\Documents and Settings\java</literal>. Batch scripts do not run
            properly when <literal>JAVA_HOME</literal> is set to such a directory.
            The solution is to install the JDK under a
            space-free path (e.g. <literal>C:\java\j2sdk...</literal> or <literal>
            D:\java\j2sdk... </literal> ) and then, set the <literal>JAVA_HOME</literal> environment variable
            accordingly.</para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Java complains about unsupported classes</emphasis> - Check
            that you are using a JRE that is at least version 1.5 since ProActive needs
            certain features which are only available starting from Java 1.5.</para>

            <programlisting><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/trouble_shooting/jdk_version_error.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>

         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

   </section>

   <section xml:id="TroubleShooting_html_loggers"><info><title xml:id="Enablingtheloggers_38">Enabling the loggers</title></info>

      <para>To enable the debugging loggers, the following log file can be
      used:</para>

      <programlisting><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/trouble_shooting/enable_debugging_loggers.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>

      <para>In this file, the relevant loggers can be uncommented (by removing
      the leading #). For example, the deployment loggers
      are activated with the following lines:</para>

      <programlisting><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/trouble_shooting/enable_deployment_loggers.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>

   </section>

   <section xml:id="dbdoclet.id.TroubleShooting_dns"><info><title xml:id="Domainenameresolutionproblems_38">Domain name resolution problems</title></info>

      <para>To work properly, ProActive requires machines to have a
      correctly configured host and domain name. If the name of a machine
      is not properly configured, then remote nodes will be unable to locate the
      machine. To work around bad-configured domain names, ProActive can be activated
      to use IP addresses through the following java property:</para>

      <programlisting><textobject><textdata fileref="code_snippets/trouble_shooting/misconfigured_domains.txt"/></textobject></programlisting>

      <para>This property should be given as parameter to Java virtual machines
      deployed on computers which have names that do not resolve properly.</para>
   </section>

   <section xml:id="dbdoclet.id.TroubleShooting_rmi_tunneling"><info><title xml:id="RMITunneling_38">RMI Tunneling</title></info>

      <para>ProActive provides RMI tunneling through ssh for crossing firewalls
      that only allow ssh connections. Here is a check-list for using rmissh
      tunneling:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para><literal>ProActive/lib/trilead-ssh2.jar</literal>
            must be included in the <literal>CLASSPATH</literal> of the
            concerned machines.</para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para>JVMs that are only accessible with ssh must be started using:
            <literal>-Dproactive.communication.protocol=rmissh</literal></para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para>A key without a passphrase must be installed on the machine
            accepting ssh connections. It should be possible to log into the
            site without using an ssh-agent and without providing a
            password.</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
   </section>

</chapter>
