<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<preface xml:id="Introduction">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<para>
		In order to make the ProActive Programming documentation easier to read, it has been split into four manuals:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">ProActive Get Started Manual</emphasis> - This manual contains an overview of ProActive Programming showing differents examples and explaining how to install the middleware.
				It also includes a tutorial teaching how to use it. This manual should be the first one to be read for beginners.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">ProActive Reference Manual</emphasis> - This manual is the main manual where the concepts of ProActive are described.
				Information on configuration and deployment are described in that manual. It also includes guides for high-level APIs usage such as Master-Worker, SMPD APIs.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">ProActive Advanced Features Manual</emphasis> - This manual describes some advanced features like Fault-Tolerance, ProActive Compile-Time Annotations or Web Services Exportation.
				In Addition, it gives information on some other high-level APIs such as Monte-Carlo or Branch and Bound APIs. Finally, it helps advanced user to extend ProActive.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">ProActive Components Manual</emphasis> - ProActive defines a component model called ProActive/GCM suitable to support the development of efficient grid applications.
				This manual therefore contains all necessary information to be able to understand and use this component model.
				This model is really linked to ProActive so a ProActive/GCM user may have to refer to the ProActive manuals form time to time.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
		These manuals should be read in the order defined above. However, this is not essential as these documentations are linked together.
		Besides, if some links seems to be dead in one of these manuals, make sure that all of them had been built previously	 (multiple html version).
		So as to build all the manuals at once, go to your ProActive <literal>compile/</literal> directory and type <literal>build[.bat] doc.ProActive.docs</literal>.
		This builds all manuals in all formats.
		If you just want to build one of these manuals in a specific format, type <literal>build[.bat]</literal> to see the possible targets and chose the one you are interested in.
	</para>
</preface>
