<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="high_level_api_tutorial"><info><title xml:id="HighLevelAPITutorials_41">High-Level API Tutorials</title></info>
	
  	<section xml:id="MWDP"><info><title xml:id="MasterWorkerDistributedPrimesApplication_41">Master-Worker DistributedPrimes Application</title></info>
		
	<para>
		In the previous Distributed Primes example, we have used 
		a basic master-worker architecture in order to distribute the
		computation. However, the algorithm used is very inefficient as
		the master has to wait for all the workers to finish the computation
		before sending a new number to be computed. In this chapter we will rewrite the 
		algorithm to take advantage of the Master-Worker API already included
		in ProActive. 
		</para>
		<para>
		The Master-Worker API aims to simplify the distribution of computations 
		which are embarrassingly parallel. The Master-Worker API hides the active object details from
		the user allowing the distribution of computation without explicitly specifying 
		the creation and deployment of active objects.  
		
	</para>
	<para>
		We will rewrite the Primes example to take advantage of the Master-Worker 
		API. Each Worker will check if a number is prime by using the simple Euclid's 
		sieve algorithm. We are not aiming for a efficient algorithm, as there are much
		faster and more complex methods of checking for primes, but for an illustration
		of how the Master-Worker API works.   
	</para>

      <para> The Master-Worker API uses a logical partition of computations and resources: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
      	<listitem> <para><emphasis> task </emphasis> - a task is logical partition of the 
	      	computation. The computation will be split into several tasks that will
	      	be assigned to workers. </para></listitem>
      	<listitem> <para> <emphasis>worker</emphasis> - a worker is logical partition of the 
	      	resources available. The workers retrieve tasks, compute them and send
	      	the results back to the master.</para>
      	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      	<figure xml:id="ArchitectureofDistributedPrimesUsingMasterWorkerAPI_41"><info><title>Architecture of Distributed Primes  Using Master-Worker API </title></info> 
		  <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>

            <imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%" fileref="guided_tour/pics/masterworker/DistributedPrimesMWdia.jpg" format="JPG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
     <section xml:id="Applicationcomponents_41"><info><title>Application components</title></info>
     	  
      	<para>
      		The general simple algorithm for using the Master-Worker API is the following:
      	</para>
      		<orderedlist>
	      		<listitem><para>Define the resources</para></listitem>
      			<listitem><para>Define the master</para></listitem>
      			<listitem><para>Define the tasks</para></listitem>
      			<listitem><para>Tell the master to solve the tasks</para></listitem>
      			<listitem><para>Retrieve the results from the workers</para></listitem>
      		</orderedlist>
      <para>
      	While this is the basic structure possible with the Master-Worker API, 
     	more complex algorithms are of course possible. 
      </para>
    <para>
		We follow this algorithm in our simple example.
	</para>	
	<para>
		First we define the resources to be used by specifying a deployment  descriptor:
	</para>
	
     	<programlisting xml:lang="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="./automatic_snippets/mw_primes_resources.snip"/></textobject></programlisting>
	
	
	<para>To learn how deployment descriptors work read <xref linkend="deployment_guide_CMA"/>
	and <xref linkend="XML_Descriptors"/>. </para>
	
	<para>After specifying the resources we need to create a master to coordinate the
	computation: </para>
	
     	<programlisting xml:lang="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="./automatic_snippets/mw_primes_master_creation.snip"/></textobject></programlisting>
	
	<para>The master has as a type <literal>ComputePrime</literal> which is a
	inner class that extends the <literal>Task</literal> interface. To create
	the master we need to specify a task the master will control and the return
	type of the method <literal>run()</literal> in the task (in our case <literal>
	Long</literal>).</para>
	
	<para>
		We define a task by implementing the interface
		<literal> Task</literal> and overriding the method
		<literal>run(WorkerMemory memory)</literal>. The
		method <literal>run(WorkerMemory memory)</literal>
		is designed to hold the computation part of the task.
		In our case it returns a type <literal>Long</literal>
		after checking if the number passed to the constructor 
		is prime.
		
	</para>

     	<programlisting xml:lang="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="./automatic_snippets/primes_distributedmw_task.snip"/></textobject></programlisting>

	<para>
		Because we do not know ahead of time how many primes numbers 
		we have in an interval we set a number of tasks <literal>
		NUMBER_OF_TASKS</literal> that reprezents the number of
		numbers to be checked in one run. Then we assign the tasks to the
		workers, calculate how many primes numbers we found and 
		display them. We repeat the same process until the desired
		number of prime numbers has been found.  
	</para>
	
	<para>Following is the code for the entire application. As
	you may notice it is much shorter than the previous example
	and it does not use any explicit active object instantiation.
	Instead we just specify a deployment descriptor and ProActive
	takes care of the rest.  </para>

     	<programlisting xml:lang="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="./automatic_snippets/primes_distributedmw_example.snip"/></textobject></programlisting>
	
	</section>
	<section xml:id="RunningmasterworkerDistributedPrimes_41"><info><title>Running master-worker Distributed Primes</title></info>
	
		
	    <para> To compile and run the application you need the 
		<literal> DistributedPrimesMW </literal>class and to
		include the following jar files: 
		  	<literal>ProActive/dist/lib/ProActive.jar</literal>,
          	<literal>ProActive/dist/lib/javassist.jar</literal>,
          		<literal>ProActive/dist/lib/log4j.jar</literal>, 
          		<literal>ProActive/dist/lib/xercesImpl.jar</literal>, 
          		<literal>ProActive/dist/lib/fractal.jar</literal>,  
          		and <literal>ProActive/dist/lib/bouncycastle.jar</literal>
           and explicitly set the Java security policy with the  <literal>-Djava.security.policy=pathToFile</literal>
           and the logging policy with  <literal>-Dlog4j.configuration=file:proactive-log4j</literal>.
            The steps necessary are explained in <xref linkend="Installation"/>.
            </para>
 		<para>	The command line for running the application is: </para> 
	<para>
			<screen>
java -Djava.security.policy=proactive.java.policy -Dlog4j.configuration=file:proactive-log4j DistributedPrimesMW</screen>
 	</para>
	</section>
	 </section>
</chapter>