<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="WSDoc"><info><title xml:id="ExportingActiveObjectsasWebServices_29">Exporting active objects and components as Web Services</title></info>
  

  <section xml:id="WS_Overwiew"><info><title xml:id="Overview_290">Overview</title></info>
    

    <para>This feature allows to expose an active object or a component as a web service and thus, to call it
    from any client written in any foreign language.</para>

    <para>Indeed, applications written in C#, for instance, cannot communicate
    with ProActive applications. We have chosen web services technology to
    enable interoperability because they are based on XML and HTTP. Thus, any
    active object can be accessible from any enabled web services language.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="Principles_29"><info><title>Principles</title></info>
    

    <para>A <emphasis role="bold">web service</emphasis> is a software entity,
    providing one or several functionalities, that can be exposed, discovered
    and accessed over the network. Moreover, web services technology allows
    heterogeneous applications to communicate and exchange data in a remotely
    way. In our case, the useful elements, of web services are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The SOAP Message</emphasis></para>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>SOAP</primary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>The SOAP message is used to exchange XML based data over the
        internet. It can be sent via HTTP and provides a serialization format
        for communicating over a network.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The HTTP Server</emphasis></para>

        <para>HTTP is the standard web protocol generally used over the 80
        port. In order to receive SOAP messages, you can either install an HTTP
        server that will be responsible of the data transfer or use the default HTTP server
		  which is a Jetty server. However, This server is not sufficient to treat a SOAP request.
		  For this, you also need a SOAP engine.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The SOAP Engine</emphasis></para>

        <para>A SOAP Engine is the mechanism responsible of making transparent
        the unmarshalling of the request and the marshalling of the response.
        Thus, the service developer doesn't have to worry with SOAP.
		  In our case, we can use Axis2 or CXF which can be installed into any HTTP server.
		  </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The client</emphasis></para>

        <para>Client's role is to consume a web service. It is the producer of
        the SOAP message. The client developer doesn't have to worry about how
        the service is implemented. The Axis2 java library provides classes to
		  easily invoke a service (see examples).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><figure xml:id="SOAP_call_steps"><info><title>Steps taken when an active object is called via SOAP</title></info>
        

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%" fileref="webservices/provider_en.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="PrerequisiteInstallingtheWebServerandtheSOAP"><info><title>Pre-requisite: Installing the Web Server and the SOAP engine</title></info>

  <para>
  If you want to expose your active objects or components on the local embedded Jetty server or on Jetty servers deployed during your deployment, you just have to deploy proactive using
  the <literal>build deploy</literal> command into the <literal>compile</literal> directory. If you want to expose them on an other http
  server, you have to build the <literal>proactive.war</literal> archive.
  For this, you have to go into your <literal>compile</literal> directory of your ProActive home and type <literal>build proActiveWar</literal>.
  The <literal>proactive.war</literal> file will be built into the <literal>dist</literal> directory.</para>

  <para>If you have chosen to use the default Jetty server, then you have nothing else to do. Jetty server will automatically take files it needs.</para>

  <para>If you have chosen to use your own HTTP server, then you just have to copy the proactive.war file into the <literal>webapp</literal> directory of your HTTP server.
  Some HTTP servers need to be restarted to take into account
  this new web application but some others like Tomcat can handle hot deployment and, thus, do not need to be restarted.</para>

  <warning>
  <para>if you use your own HTTP server, you have to be aware that the Jetty server will be launched. Most of ProActive examples are launched
  with the option '-Dproactive.http.port=8080' which specifies Jetty port. So, if you want to use your own server on port 8080, you have to modify the jetty port in
  launching scripts or to change the port of your own server.</para>
   </warning>

  </section>

	

  <section xml:id="Stepstoexposeanactiveobjectasa_29"><info><title>Steps to expose or unexpose an active object as a web services</title></info>
    

    <para>The steps for exporting and using an active object as a web service
    are the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>Write your active object or your component in a classic way as below:</para>

			<programlisting language="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="automatic_snippets/webservices_AO_1.snip" /></textobject></programlisting>
			<para>
				or
			</para>
			<programlisting language="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="automatic_snippets/webservices_Component_1.snip" /></textobject></programlisting>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
			<para>Once the element created and activated, a <emphasis role="bold">WebServicesFactory</emphasis> object has to be instantiated: </para>
			<programlisting language="java">WebServicesFactory wsf = AbstractWebServicesFactory.getWebServicesFactory("axis2");</programlisting>
			<para>or</para>
			<programlisting language="java">WebServicesFactory wsf = AbstractWebServicesFactory.getWebServicesFactory("cxf");</programlisting>
			<para>or else</para>
			<programlisting language="java">WebServicesFactory wsf = AbstractWebServicesFactory.getDefaultWebServicesFactory();</programlisting>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Then, you have to instantiate a <emphasis role="bold">WebServices</emphasis> object as follows: </para>
			<programlisting language="java">WebServices ws = wsf.getWebServices(myUrl);</programlisting>
			<para>If you want to use the local Jetty server to expose your active object or your component, you can use the following line
			to retrieve the good URL:</para>
			<programlisting language="java">String myUrl = AbstractWebServicesFactory.getLocalUrl();</programlisting>
			<para>This will get the Jetty port which is a random port and build the url.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>And finally, you can used one of the <literal>WebServices</literal> methods: </para>
			<programlisting language="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="automatic_snippets/WebServices_Methods.snip" /></textobject></programlisting>

        <para>where:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">o</emphasis> is the active
                object</para>
            </listitem>
				<listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">component</emphasis> is the component</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">url</emphasis> is the url of the
                web server (typically http://localhost:8080/).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">urn</emphasis> is the service name
                which will identify the active object on the server.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">methods</emphasis> is a String or a Method array
                containing the methods you want to make accessible. If
                this parameter is null (or is absent), all the public methods will be
                exposed.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para><emphasis role="bold">componentName</emphasis> the first part of the service name
               which will identify the component on the server. The service will be exposed at the address
               http://[host]:[port]/proactive/services/componentName_interfaceName</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">interfaceNames</emphasis> is a String array
                containing the interfaces of the component you want to make accessible. If
                this parameters is null (or is absent), all the functional server interfaces of the component will be exposed.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="exposeonremotejettyservers_29"><info><title>Exposing as a web service on remote Jetty servers launched during the deployment</title></info>
	<para>
		When you call the exposition of your active object or your component,
		the Axis2 servlet or the CXF one is deployed on the local Jetty server. It is therefore possible
		to expose your object locally without doing anything else.
	</para>
	<para>
		Now, let us assume that your active object (or component) is deployed on a remote node.
		In that case, you have a running jetty server on the remote host containing this node but no servlet has been deployed on it.
		So, if you want to expose your active object on the remote host, you will have to make a small modification of the previous piece of code.
	</para>
	<para>
		The web service extension provides classes that implements the <literal>InitActive</literal> interface which are in charge of deploying the CXF or the Axis2 servlet on the host
		where your object has been initialized. Thus, you just have to instantiate you active object or your component using this implementation of <literal>InitActive</literal>.
	</para>

	<programlisting language="java">// Get the CXF InitActive in charge of deploying the CXF Servlet
InitActive cxfInitActive = WebServicesInitActiveFactory.getInitActive("cxf");
MyObject o = (MyObject) PAActiveObject.newActive(
	MyObject.class.getName(), null, new Object[] {}, myNode, cxfInitActive, null);</programlisting>

	<para>For the component, it would look as follows:</para>

	<programlisting language="java">// Get the Axis2 InitActive in charge of deploying the Axis2 Servlet
InitActive axis2InitActive = WebServicesInitActiveFactory.getInitActive("axis2");
Component myComponent = myGenericFactory.newFcInstance(myComponentType,
	new ControllerDescription("myControllerName", Constants.PRIMITIVE),
	new ContentDescription(MyComponent.class.getName(), null, axis2InitActive, null), myNode);</programlisting>

	<para>
		Concerning components, there exists another way to do that using controllers. Indeed, the webservice extension also provides a customized controller
		that will deploy the chosen servlet at component start.
	</para>

	<para>So, you can proceed as follows:</para>

	<programlisting language="java">ControllerDescription cd = new ControllerDescription("myControllerName", Constants.PRIMITIVE,
	"&lt;your ProActive Home&gt;/src/Extensions/" +
	"org/objectweb/proactive/extensions/webservices/cxf/initialization/cxf-component-config.xml");
Component myComp = myGenericFactory.newFcInstance(myComponentType, cd,
	new ContentDescription(MyComponent.class.getName()));</programlisting>

	<para>
		The <literal>cxf-component-config.xml</literal> file just redefines the controller to be the
		<literal>org.objectweb.proactive.extensions.webservices.cxf.initialization.CXFProActiveLifeCycleControllerImpl</literal>.
		For using the <literal>org.objectweb.proactive.extensions.webservices.axis2.initialization.Axis2ProActiveLifeCycleControllerImpl</literal>,
		use the file located at <literal>"&lt;your ProActive Home&gt;/src/Extensions/org/objectweb/proactive/extensions/webservices/axis2/initialization/axis2-component-config.xml"</literal>
	</para>

	<para>
		Now, let us assume that your active object or your component is deployed on a node or locally and that you want to expose it on a host where another node is deployed.
		On this host, there is only a running Jetty server without any web services servlet.
		In order to deploy the CXF or Axis2 servlet on it, you can use the following code:
	</para>

	<programlisting language="java">WebServicesInitActiveFactory.getInitActive("cxf").initServlet(myNode);</programlisting>

	<para>
		Then, you can expose your active object as a web service as in <xref linkend="Stepstoexposeanactiveobjectasa_29"/>.
	</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="Accessingtheservices_29"><info><title>Accessing the services</title></info>
    

    <para>Once the active object or the component deployed, you can access it via any web service client (such as C#, SoapUI, Axis2 API, CXF API...) or with your favorite browser
    (only if the returned type of your service methods are primitive types).</para>

    <para>First of all, the client will get the WSDL file matching this active
    object. This WSDL file is the 'identity card' of the service. It contains
    the web service public interfaces and its location. Generally, WSDL files
    are used to generate a proxy to the service. For example, for a given
    service, say 'compute', you can get the WSDL document at <code>http://localhost:8080/proactive/services/compute?wsdl</code>.</para>

    <para>Now that this client knows what and where to call the service, it
    will send a SOAP message to the web server. The web server looks into the
    message and performs the right call. Then, it returns the response into another
    SOAP message to the client.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="Limitations_29"><info><title>Limitations</title></info>
    
    <para>Contrary to the previous version of the active object exposition using Apache SOAP, this new version which uses Axis2 or CXF can handle complex types.
	 That is, with this version, you can implement a service which exposes a method returning or taking in argument an instance of any class.
	 However, the class of this instance has to respect some criterion due to the serialization and CXF/Axis2 restrictions:</para>
	 <itemizedlist>
		 <listitem><para>This class has to be serializable</para></listitem>
		 <listitem><para>This class has to supply a no-args constructor and preferably empty</para></listitem>
		 <listitem><para>All the fields of this class has to be private or protected</para></listitem>
		 <listitem><para>This class has to supply public getters and setters for each field.
		 These getter and setter methods have to be in this class and not in one of its super classes.</para></listitem>
	 </itemizedlist>


    <para>
		Axis2 and CXF are not fully compatible. In particular, clients behave differently.
		Axis2 client uses to send SOAP requests using "argn" as name for the n-th argument of the requested method. However, CXF creates the WSDL
		service using parameter names as written into the Java code. Thus, there is a difference of names and the service cannot find argument names in the SOAP
		message matching with the argument names of the requested method. Null value is therefore used as parameters.
		To easily solve this issue, you can change the argument names of your service to match with "argn". If you cannot change the service, you have to
		use another client as those used in the ProActive extension.
	 </para>
	 <para>
		If you want to use the CXF client provided by ProActive for calling an Axis2 service, you will also face difficulties since this client waits for a returned SOAP message
		that the Axis2 service will not return for a void method. One thing but not the best you can do, is to modify ProActive CXF client in order to eat the exception
		for oneWayCall. This is not the best solution since other exceptions will be eaten too.
	 </para>

	 <para>
		 In a general manner, we advise you to use the same framework for the exposition as a web service and for the client consuming this service.
	 </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="AsimpleexampleHelloWorld_29"><info><title>A simple example: Hello World</title></info>
    

    <section xml:id="HelloWorldwebservicecode_29"><info><title>Hello World web service code</title></info>
      

      <para>Let's start with a simple example, an Hello world active object
      exposed as a web service:</para>

      <programlisting language="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="automatic_snippets/webservices_AO_2.snip" /></textobject></programlisting>

      <para>The active object <literal>hw</literal> has been deployed as a web
      service on the web server located at
      <literal>http://localhost:8080/proactive/services/</literal> and its service name is
		<literal>"MyHelloWorldService"</literal>. The accessible service
      method are <literal>putTextToSayAndConfirm, putTextToSay and sayText</literal>.
		You can see its wsdl file through the
      <literal>http://localhost:8080/proactive/services/MyHelloWorldService?wsdl</literal> and you
      call the <literal>helloWorld</literal> method with your browser through, for example,
      <literal>http://localhost:8080/proactive/services/MyHelloWorldService/sayText</literal>.</para>


      <para>If you want to expose a method which requires arguments, you can call using the same link as previously but
      adding <literal>?[arg0]=[value]&amp;[arg1]=[value]...</literal> where [argn] is the name of the n-th argument
      as written in the wsdl file.</para>

		<para>You can also call a webservice using the ProActive client which uses, depending on the chosen framework, either a axis2 or a cxf client.
		Here is an example:</para>

      <programlisting language="java"><textobject><textdata fileref="automatic_snippets/webservices_AO_3.snip" /></textobject></programlisting>

      <para>Now that the server-side Web service is deployed, we can create a
      new client application in Visual Studio .NET.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="AccesswithVisualStudio_29"><info><title>Access with Visual Studio</title></info>
      

      <para/>

      <para>In your new Visual Studio Project:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the Solution Explorer window, right-click References and
          click Add Web Reference.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In the address box enter the WSDL service address, for
          example: <code> http://localhost:8080/proactive/services/HelloWorld?wsdl</code>.
	   When clicking the 'add reference' button, this will get the
          service's WSDL and creates the specific proxy to the service.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Once the web reference is added, you can use the HelloWorld
          service as an object and perform calls on it:</para>

          <programlisting language="java">...
localhost.helloWorld hw = new localhost.helloWorld();
string s = hw.helloWorld ();
...</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="CinteroperabilityanexamplewithC3D_29"><info><title>C# interoperability: an example with C3D</title></info>
    

    <section xml:id="Overview_29"><info><title>Overview</title></info>
      

      <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www-sop.inria.fr/oasis/ProActive/apps/c3d.html">C3D</link>
      is a Java benchmark application that measures the performance of a 3D
      raytracer renderer distributed over several Java virtual machines using
      ProActive. C3D is composed of several parts: the distributed engine
      (renderers) and the dispatcher that is an active objet. This dispactcher
      permits users to see the 3D scene and to collaborate. Users can send
      messages and render command to this dispatcher. This enhancement of C3D
      is to send commands to the dispatcher from any language. To perform such
      an enhancement, the Dispatcher object must be exposed as a web service
      in order to a C# client for example controls it. Only one instruction
      has been added in the main method:</para>

      <programlisting language="java">WebServices.exposeAsWebService (dispatcher, "C3DDispatcher",
                    "http://localhost:8080",  new String [] {
                    "rotateRight", "getPicture", "rotateLeft", "rotateUp",
                    "rotateDown", "getPixels", "getPixelMax", "waitForImage",
                    "spinClock", "spinUnclock", "addRandomSphere", "resetScene",
                    "registerWSUser", "unregisterWSUser"
                });</programlisting>

      <para>Once the dispatcher is deployed as a web service, we have a WSDL
      url: <code>http://localhost:8080/proactive/servlet/id=C3DDispatcher</code>. It
      will be usefull to construct the dispatcher client.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="AccesswithaCclient_29"><info><title>Access with a C# client</title></info>
      

      <para>First of all, we have to generate the service proxy following the
      steps described for the hello world access.</para>

      <para>All the SOAP calls will be managed by the generated proxy
      <literal>localhost.C3DDispatcher</literal>. <figure xml:id="Thedispatcherhandlingallcalls_29"><info><title>The dispatcher handling all calls</title></info>
          

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%" fileref="webservices/dispatcher_en.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="Dispatchermethodscallsandcallbacks_29"><info><title>Dispatcher methods calls and callbacks</title></info>
      

      <para>C# client registers to the C3D dispatcher and then can send
      commands. C3D is a collaborative application. Indeed, when a client
      performs a call, all others users must be advised by the dispatcher.
      Although dispatcher can contact ProActive applications, it cannot
      communicate with other applications (it cannot initiate the
      communication). In other words, the dispacher must communicate remotely
      with an application written in another language.</para>

      <para>The answer to this problem is to use .Net web service on the C#
      user machine. Such a web service is waiting for callback requests that
      come from dispatcher. When receiving a request, the service sends it to
      the client via a .Net Remoting shared object. Thus, when the .Net web
      service receives a callback request, the C# client is updated thanks to
      propagated events.</para>

      <para>Here are screenshots of the user application: <figure xml:id="classic_pa_application"><info><title>The first screenshot is a classic ProActive
          application</title></info>
          

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%" fileref="webservices/scc3djava.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure> <figure xml:id="CapplicationcommunicatingviaSOAP_29"><info><title>C# application communicating via SOAP</title></info>
          

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%" fileref="webservices/scC3dcs.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>

            <caption><para>The application is using the same dispatcher the
            ProActive user uses.</para></caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>


	</section>

    <section xml:id="DownloadtheCexample_29"><info><title>Download the C# example</title></info>


      <para>You can find <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://proactive.inria.fr/userfiles/file/apps/C3DCSharp.zip">here</link>
      the whole C# Visual Studio .Net project. N.B: In order to run this
      project, you must install the Microsoft IIS server.</para>
    </section>

 </section>

</chapter>
